angiogenesis is the creation of new
blood vessels tumors use it to keep
growing well our fatty tissue also needs
a blood supply to expand so might an
anti-angiogenic approach work for weight
loss too I'll explore that in this video
and the next
[Music]
many of our modern Frontline therapies
against cancer incorporate
anti-angiogenesis strategies from the
Greek words angio meaning vessel and
Genesis meaning creation so
anti-angiogenesis is opposing the
creation of blood vessels in other words
fighting cancer by cutting off tumor
supply lines
some cancers are only able to grow to
about the size of the tip of a ballpoint
pen without a blood supply tumor growth
then stalls autopsy studies show that
virtually everyone has these tiny tumors
in them by age 70. cancer without
disease can therefore be considered the
normal State during aging to commandeer
blood supply tumors diabolically release
angiogenic factors chemicals that cause
new blood vessels to sprout towards the
cancer
once a blood vessel reaches the tumor
and attaches it's Off to the Races the
tumor can then take off exponentially by
starving cancer of its blood supply
chemotherapy that blocks this process
can sometimes cause tumors to shrink but
ideally we wouldn't have to wait until
such a late stage to nip them in the bud
that's where our diet can come in many
of the phytonutrients we know and love
in tea spices berries broccoli and beans
have anti-angiogenic properties given
the power of plants the foundation of an
anti-angiogenic approach to cancer has
been considered a whole food plant-based
diet
but the title of this video is targeting
angiogenesis to lose weight what does
this have to do with obesity well think
about it tumors aren't the only tissue
in the body with expanding volume the
average tumor picked up by mammograms is
only about the size of a marble and it
can take breast cancer decades to grow
whereas over feed people and you can
easily add an entire pound of fatty
tissue in a matter of days and body fat
is highly vascularized each fat cell in
our body is essentially surrounded by
tiny blood vessels enlarged liposuction
operations a third of what's vacuumed
out is straight blood
throughout adulthood our fatty tissue is
constantly remodeling expanding and
shrinking based on our day-to-day energy
demands this requires the development
and Retreat of extensive networks of new
blood vessels the human body already
contains 60 000 miles of blood vessels
imagine how many more miles have to be
constructed when we gain weight without
angiogenesis without the sprouting of
all these new blood vessels we wouldn't
be able to add all that fat now do you
see where this is all going
to expand fat cells release the same
kinds of chemicals that tumors do to
swell its blood supply fatty tissue is
so angiogenic open heart surgeons have
even tried grafting fatty tissue
directly on the heart after a heart
attack in hopes it would Foster the
growth of arteries to bypass the
blockages you can take fat samples from
obese individuals during bariatric
surgery place them on living membranes
of fertile chicken eggs and within a
week the fat is literally engulfed in
blood vessels that may help explain why
excess body fat can accelerate cancer
growth obesity increases the risk of
more than a dozen different cancers
increasing the overall risk of getting
and then dying from cancer by about 20
percent all those angiogenic factors
released from our increasing body fat
May spill out into our bloodstream
resulting in higher blood levels among
overweight individuals which can then
drop back down when we lose weight so
maybe we can get the best of both worlds
if we treated obesity like a tumor using
anti-angio genetics strategies to
prevent the expansion of our fat mass in
the first place there are
anti-angiogenic drugs as well as
anti-angiogenic Foods we'll explore both
next
[Music]